Finding Aid for John B. Swainson Papers 1943-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John B. Swainson Papers 1943-1975 1960-1962
Swainson, John Burley, 1925-
Democratic governor of Michigan, 1961-1963; gubernatorial office files, campaign files, papers from his career as state senator and lieutenant governor.
8667 Aa 2 Ac
71.5 linear feet in 73 boxes
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of John B. Swainson (donor no. 3987 ) and has come to the library in various accessions, 1963-1971.
The collection is open for research.
John B. Swainson was born July 31, 1925 in Windsor, Ontario. He grew up in Port Huron, Michigan, where he attended the public schools and was active in sports. During World War II, he served with the 95th Infantry Division under General George S. Patton. Severely wounded by a land mine explosion, Swainson lost both of his legs to amputation.
Upon his discharge from the service, Swainson entered Olivet College. Here he met and married Alice Nielsen of Detroit, Michigan. Moving to North Carolina for medical reasons, Swainson attended and graduated from the University of North Carolina (LLB; 1951). Upon graduation, Swainson returned to Michigan and set up law practice in Detroit.
In Michigan Swainson demonstrated his interest in Democratic politics. In 1954, he was elected to the Michigan Senate from the 18th District (the northwest section of Wayne County). He was reelected in 1956 and developed a close working relationship with Democratic governor, G. Mennen Williams. In 1958, he was elected lieutenant governor; and in 1960, after Williams decided against reelection, Swainson won his party's nomination for governor. In the fall election, he defeated the Republican challenger Paul Bagwell in a close election. He became at age 35 the second youngest man to hold the office of governor and the first who was not native born.
During his term in office, Swainson sought to carry out the Democratic program of his predecessor, G. Mennen Williams. The debate focused primarily on finances and the need to overhaul the state's system of taxation. As it stood, monies for state government were raised through an inequitable combination of sales and property taxes. Swainson urged passage of a comprehensive package of fiscal and tax reform legislation that would shift the burden of taxation off the poor and middle class and onto businesses and the state's wealthier citizens. A cornerstone of his program was a state income tax, but because of Republican opposition in the legislature, the Swainson tax package was defeated. One result of the defeat was that local communities (notably Detroit), strapped for funds, began implementing their own city income tax ordinances. When the suburbs of Detroit drafted legislation (the Bowman bill) that would have prevented cities such as Detroit from taxing non-residents whose place of employment was in the city, Swainson vetoed the bill. As a consequence in the following election, he lost a substantial portion of the suburban vote that was to have been critical to his reelection.
Because of the opposition of the Republican legislature, the Swainson administration is known less for the legislation passed during his term than for his use of the office of governor, first through his power to veto what he termed "special interest" legislation and secondly, through his power to issue executive orders. Notable examples of Swainson executive orders provided for the establishment of the first Michigan Commission on the Status of Women, the implementation of a Governor's Code of Fair Employment Practices for all state agencies, the creation of a "Keep Michigan Beautiful" organization devoted to environmental matters, and the appointment of the Governor's Constitutional Convention Preparatory Commission. Swainson also used the prestige of his office to articulate his liberal, Democratic beliefs. As governor of an important northern state, Swainson was forthright in the press and at various Governors' conferences in his support of the civil rights movement and vocal in his abhorrence of the segregationist practices of the south.
Undoubtedly, the most important event of Swainson's administration was the calling of a constitutional convention. Michigan then operated under a 1908 constitution which was badly outdated and was blamed by many for the state's inability to solve its financial difficulties during the 1950s. During 1960 and before, citizen groups gathered petitions, and in April 1961, the people voted to call a constitutional convention. A primary election was held in July and a general election of delegates in September. The convention itself was seated from October through May 1962. During the summer months, an address to the people was prepared, and then on August 1, 1962, the convention reassembled to vote on this address and the slight changes that had been recommended in the preceding weeks. The convention again approved the document, then adjourned. The constitution was submitted to a vote of the people in April 1963 where it passed by an uncomfortably narrow margin.
Swainson's election in 1960 was close; in 1962, he was opposed by the popular automobile executive George Romney. Swainson lost, and contributing to his defeat, in addition to Romney's popularity, were the state's continuing financial woes and the fact that the Michigan's chief executive had been a Democrat since 1948.
In April 1965, Swainson was elected judge of the Third Circuit and reelected in 1966. In June 1969. Swainson and a group of concerned citizens founded NARCO (Narcotics Addiction Rehabilitation Co-ordinating Organization), a citizens organization formed to co-ordinate the efforts of various fragmented groups and programs attempting to combat the growing problem of drug use and abuse. On November 3, 1970, Swainson was elected to an 8-year term on the Michigan Supreme Court. In January 1973, he was selected to serve as Deputy Chief Justice. He resigned from office in 1975 following his conviction by a federal jury of perjury during an investigation into a charge that as justice he had accepted a bribe.
After serving a brief 60 day sentence in a Detroit halfway house, Swainson retired to private life. When his license to practice law was restored, he worked as a mediator and arbitrator, and became active in the Michigan Historical Commission, serving for a time as its president.
John Swainson died May 15, 1994.
The John B. Swainson collection consists of four subgroups of files: pre-gubernatorial (covering the period of 1943 to 1960), gubernatorial (covering his one-term, two-year tenure as the state's chief executive), post-gubernatorial (covering the years since he left the governor's office, 1963 to 1975), and visual materials.
The great bulk of the collection is the gubernatorial subgroup documenting the last months of Swainson's term as lieutenant governor under Governor G. Mennen Williams, the 1960 campaign for governor, his gubernatorial administration, and his unsuccessful campaign for re-election. The importance of the collection, as with all gubernatorial records, is its documentation of public policy issues of the early 1960s and the relationship of the governor to the legislature, to the heads of the state's various boards and commissions, to the federal government, and to the citizens of Michigan.
Subjects:
Civil defense.; Civil rights--Michigan.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Drug abuse--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Governors--Michigan.; Judges--Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan. Lieutenant Governor.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Governors--Michigan.; Governors--Michigan.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.; Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Political elections--1960.; Political elections--1962.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Swainson, Alice.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Swainson family.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Contributors: Visual Material
Poinier, Arthur Best.; Williams, Frank.
Sound Recordings
Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1962.; Governors--Michigan.; Mental health.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Bartlett, Lynn M. (Lynn Mahlon), 1904-1970.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.
Genre/Form:
Cartoons.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Pre-gubernatorial Career
  The Pre-gubernatorial subgroup includes the papers created by John Swainson prior to his assuming the office of governor. Largely files from his one-term as lieutenant governor, including his 1960 campaign papers, this subgroup is interesting for Swainson's letters to his parents while serving during the Second World War. For documentation of the politics and government of the 1950s, the researcher is directed first to the papers of G. Mennen Williams.
  - Personal/World War II
    - Biographical material (Box 1)
      (includes oral history transcript from Kennedy Library covering the period of 1958-1963)
    - War letters
      - September-December 1943 (Box 1)
      - January-March 1944 (Box 1)
      - April-July 1944 (Box 1)
      - August-November 1944 (Box 1)
      - December 1944-October 1945 (Box 1)
    - Family letters (war period) 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Olivet College 1946 (Box 1)
  - State Senate/Lieutenant Governor
    - Various: press releases, speeches, correspondence, etc
      - Democratic Party of Michigan 1957-1959 (Box 1)
      - Democratic State Campaign 1958 (Box 1)
      - State Senate (various issues) 1957-1958 (Box 1)
      - Press releases 1957-1959, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Speeches 1959-1960, 15 folders (Box 1)
      - Schedules 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (constituent mail) 1959, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1960, 5 folders (Box 2)
        (constituent and congratulatory mail; sampled)
    - Subjects 1957-1960
      - Aging, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Carver School (Box 3)
      - Civil defense, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Civil rights (Box 3)
      - Conservation (Box 3)
      - Consumer protection (Box 3)
      - Corrections (Box 3)
      - Economic growth, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Education-Institutions of higher learning (Box 3)
      - Employment (Box 3)
      - Ethnic groups (Box 3)
      - Hare, James (Box 3)
      - Health (Box 3)
      - Highways (Box 3)
      - Highway safety (Box 3)
      - Industrial development (Box 3)
      - Insurance (Box 3)
      - Juvenile delinquency (Box 3)
      - Labor (Box 3)
      - Mental health (Box 3)
      - Migratory labor (Box 3)
      - Physically handicapped, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Social welfare (Box 3)
      - Taxes (Box 3)
      - Tourism (Box 3)
      - Upper Peninsula (Box 3)
      - Veterans (Box 3)
      - Veterans Trust Fund (Box 3)
    - Boards and Commissions 1959-1960
      - Administration (Box 4)
      - Aeronautics (Box 4)
      - Agriculture (Box 4)
      - Attorney General (Box 4)
      - Auditor General (Box 4)
      - Banking (Box 4)
      - Bar (State) of Michigan (Box 4)
      - Civil Defense (Michigan Office (Box 4)
      - Civil Service (Box 4)
      - Civil War Centennial Commission (Box 4)
      - Conservation (Box 4)
      - Corrections (Box 4)
      - Cosmetology (Box 4)
      - Council of State Governments (Box 4)
      - Economic Development (Box 4)
      - Employment Security Commission (Michigan) (Box 4)
      - Executive (Box 4)
      - Federal
        - Hart, Philip A (Box 4)
        - House of Representatives (Box 4)
        - Senate (Box 4)
      - Health
        - General (Box 4)
        - Hospital survey and construction (Box 4)
      - Highways (Box 4)
      - Insurance (Box 4)
      - Labor Mediation Board (Box 4)
      - Legal assistance (Box 4)
      - Liquor Control Commission (Box 4)
      - Mental Health (Box 4)
      - Michigan State University (Box 4)
      - Mortuary Science (Box 4)
      - Municipal Finance Commission (Box 4)
      - Plumbing (Box 4)
      - Police, State (Box 4)
      - Public Instruction (Box 4)
      - Public Service Commission (Box 4)
      - Revenue (Box 4)
      - Secretary of State (Box 4)
      - Social Welfare (Box 4)
      - State Property (Box 4)
      - Tourist Council (Box 4)
      - Traffic Safety (Box 4)
      - University of Michigan (Box 4)
      - Veterans (general) (Box 4)
      - Veterans Trust Fund (Box 4)
      - Waterways Commission (Box 4)
    - Legislature
      - Legislative agents (Box 4)
      - District maps (Box 4)
      - Invocations (Box 4)
      - Legislation supported and opposed (Box 4)
      - Press representatives (Box 4)
  - Campaign for Governor 1959-1960
    - Strategy, organization, etc. 1960 (Box 4)
    - Campaign letters and mailings 1960 (Box 4)
    - Newsletter 1960 (Box 4)
    - Democratic State Central Committee 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - Policy reports 1960 (Box 4)
    - Democratic platform 1960 (Box 4)
    - Presidential campaign (Box 4)
      (includes John F. Kennedy letters)
    - Republican campaign material 1958-1960 (Box 4)
    - Transition from Lieutenant Governor to Governor 1960 (Box 4)
  - Clippings/scrapbooks (Box 5)
    - Scrapbooks
      (contains clippings and photos)
      - 1956 (Box 5)
      - January 1957-March 1958 (Box 5)
      - March-April 1958 (Box 5)
      - August-November 1960 (Box 5)
    - Clippings (various), pre-1961 (Box 5)
- Gubernatorial Career (1961-1963) 1960-1963
  The gubernatorial papers consist primarily of two chronological series (for 1961 and 1962). Each of these is further divided into subseries either reflecting the governor's administrative relationships (with the state's boards and commissions, the federal government, and the legislature) or general topics of current interest or pertaining to the governor's role as the state's chief executive. Beyond these two chronological series, there are staff files for some, but not all of the key Swainson aides. One important staff member whose files form part of this subseries is Richard Miller who was the governor's Legislative Assistant, and as such was responsible for maintaining background information on various pieces of legislation. His files include memoranda from various state agencies on their perspective of needed legislation.
  - 1961 files
    - Boards and Commissions
      - Administrative Board
        - General (Box 6)
        - Meeting files January-August, 1961, 19 folders (Box 6)
        - Meeting files September-December 1961, 9 folders (Box 7)
        - Reports, 12 folders (Box 7)
        - Agriculture Department (Box 7)
        - Conservation (Box 7)
        - Health (Box 7)
        - Highway (Box 7)
        - Social Welfare (Box 7)
        - State Police (Box 7)
      - Administration, Department of
        - General (Box 7)
        - Surplus property (Box 7)
      - Aeronautics (Box 7)
      - Aging Commission
        - General, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Housing (Box 7)
      - Agriculture
        - General, 4 folders (Box 8)
        - Short weights and measures (Box 8)
      - Alcoholism (Box 8)
      - Architects, Professional Engineers, Land Surveyors (Box 8)
      - Athletic Board of Control, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Attorney General
        - General (Box 8)
        - Adams, Paul (Box 8)
        - Carpet fraud, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Samuel Olsen slush fund (Box 8)
        - Opinions (Box 8)
      - Auditor General (Box 8)
      - Banking, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Barbers, Board of Examiners of
        - General (Box 8)
        - Upper Peninsula barber inspection (Box 8)
      - Basic Science, Board of Examiners of (Box 8)
      - Bridge Commission (Box 8)
      - Building Commission (Box 8)
      - Chiropody, Board of Registration in (Box 8)
      - Chiropractic Examiners, State Board of (Box 8)
      - Civil Service Commission
        - Frank DeWald, Director, file (Box 8)
        - Alphabetical file (Box 8)
        - Group insurance (Box 8)
      - Civil War Centennial Commission
        - General (Box 8)
        - Letters (Box 8)
        - Reports, memoranda, etc (Box 8)
      - Colleges and Universities
        - Central Michigan University (Box 9)
        - Eastern Michigan University (Box 9)
        - Ferris Institute (Box 9)
        - Grand Valley College, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Michigan College of Mining and Technology (Box 9)
        - Michigan State University (Box 9)
        - Northern Michigan University (Box 9)
        - University of Michigan
          - General (Box 9)
          - Institute of Science and Technology (Box 9)
        - Wayne State University (Box 9)
        - Western Michigan University (Box 9)
      - Conservation
        - Gerald E. Eddy file (Box 9)
        - General, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Commercial fishing (Box 9)
        - Interstate Oil Compact Commission (Box 9)
      - Corporation and Securities Commission (Box 9)
      - Corrections
        - Gus Harrison file (Box 9)
        - General (Box 9)
        - Michigan Reformatory (Box 9)
        - Pardons and Paroles (Box 9)
        - State Prison of Southern Michigan (Box 9)
      - Cosmetology Board, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Crippled Children Commission (Box 9)
      - Dentistry (Box 9)
      - Economic Development Commission
        - General (Box 9)
        - Alphabetical file, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Economic Future of Michigan
          - Adrian Defense Plant (Box 10)
          - Badger (W.L.) Associates (Box 10)
          - Gemmer Manufacturing Company (Box 10)
          - Motor Wheel (Box 10)
          - Norge Division, Borg-Warner Corporation (Box 10)
        - Governor's Conference on Economic Needs of the Upper Peninsula (Box 10)
        - Industrial Ambassadors (Box 10)
        - Michigan Week (Box 10)
        - Mine Executives Meeting April 20, 1961 (Box 10)
      - Education, State Board of
        - General (Box 10)
        - Michigan Rehabilitation Institute (Box 10)
      - Electrical Administrative Board (Box 10)
      - Employment Security Commission
        - General, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Meeting on S.B. 1349 (Employment Security Act) (Box 10)
        - Federal legislation, H.R. 3864 (temporary unemployment compensation) (Box 10)
      - Employment Security Appeal Board (Box 10)
      - Escheats, State Board of (Box 10)
      - Fair Commission, Michigan State
        - General (Box 10)
        - State Fair Centennial Awards (Box 10)
        - State Fair dates (Box 10)
        - Upper Peninsula fair (Box 10)
      - Fair Employment Practices Commission
        - General (Box 10)
        - Code of Fair Practices (Box 10)
        - Race track industry (Box 10)
      - Great Lakes Commission (Box 11)
      - Health Department
        - General, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Symond Gottlieb case (Box 11)
        - Bay County Medical Care Facility (Box 11)
      - Higher Education Assistance Authority (Box 11)
      - Highway Department
        - General (Box 11)
        - John C. Mackie file (Box 11)
        - Employment policies (charges of discrimination) (Box 11)
      - Historical Commission (Box 11)
      - Insurance Department
        - General (Box 11)
        - Frank Blackford file (Box 11)
        - Maccabees Mutual Life Insurance Company (Box 11)
      - International Bridge Authority of Michigan (Box 11)
      - Interstate Cooperation, Commission on (Box 11)
      - Labor Department
        - General (Box 11)
        - Leonard School (Troy) explosion (Box 11)
        - Saginaw school disaster (Box 11)
      - Labor Mediation Board
        - General (Box 11)
        - Intertown Suburban Lines (Box 11)
        - Mt. Lebanon Hospital (Box 11)
        - Pine Rest Christian Association (Box 11)
        - Sidney Sumby Hospital (Box 11)
        - Women's Hospital (Box 11)
      - State Library
        - General (Box 12)
        - State Librarian's file (Box 12)
      - Libraries, State Board of (Box 12)
      - Lieutenant Governor (Box 12)
      - Liquor Control Commission
        - General (Box 12)
        - Alphabetical file, 4 folders (Box 12)
        - Disposable bottles (Box 12)
      - Mackinac Bridge Authority (Box 12)
      - Mackinac Island Park Commission (Box 12)
      - Medicine, State Board of Registration in (Box 12)
      - Mental Health Department
        - General (Box 12)
        - Hospitals
          - Caro State Hospital for Epileptics (Box 12)
          - Howell TB Sanatorium (Box 12)
          - Ionia State Hospital (Box 12)
          - Kalamazoo State Hospital (Box 12)
          - Plymouth State Home and Training School (Box 12)
        - Retarded Children's program (Box 12)
      - Mortuary Science Board (Box 12)
      - Municipal Finance Commission (Box 12)
      - Nursing, Michigan Board of (Box 12)
      - Optometry, State Board of Examiners in (Box 12)
      - Osteopathic Registration and Examination, Board of (Box 12)
      - Pharmacy (Box 12)
      - Plumbing Board (Box 12)
      - Police, State
        - General (Box 12)
        - Joseph A. Childs file (Box 12)
        - "Operation Abolition" film dispute
          - Background information (Box 12)
          - Correspondence, 1 folders (Box 12)
          - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Port of Detroit (Box 13)
      - Potato Industry Council (Box 13)
      - Private Employment Agencies, State Superintendent of (Box 13)
      - Public Instruction
        - General (Box 13)
        - Lynn Bartlett file (Box 13)
        - Carver School District, Oak Park (Box 13)
        - Vocational Education Division (Box 13)
        - Youth Fitness Program (Box 13)
      - Public Service Commission
        - General (Box 13)
        - George Hill file (Box 13)
      - Racing Commission (Box 13)
      - Retirement boards
        - General (Box 13)
        - Employees Retirement System (Box 13)
        - Judges Retirement System (Box 13)
        - Legislative Retirement Board (Box 13)
        - Michigan Public School Retirement Fund (Box 13)
      - Revenue Department (Box 13)
      - Safety Commission
        - General (Box 13)
        - Gerald Shipman file (Box 13)
        - Petroleum haulers (Box 13)
        - President's Commission on Traffic Safety (Box 13)
      - Secretary of State (Box 13)
      - Social Welfare Commission
        - General (Box 13)
        - W.J. Maxey file (Box 13)
        - ADC
          - Suitable housing (Box 13)
          - Children of unemployed (Box 13)
          - Michigan State Association of Supervisors meeting re ADC for unemployed (Box 13)
        - Surplus food program (Box 13)
      - Soil Conservation Committee (Box 14)
      - Supreme Court (Box 14)
      - Tax Appeals, Board of (Box 14)
      - Tax Commission
        - General (Box 14)
        - Ironwood (Box 14)
      - Tenure Commission (Box 14)
      - Tourist Council (Box 14)
      - Treasurer, State (Box 14)
      - Tuberculosis Sanitarium Commission (Box 14)
      - Uniform State Laws, Michigan Commissioners on (Box 14)
      - Veterans Facility, Michigan (Box 14)
      - Water Resources Commission
        - General (Box 14)
        - Detroit River Pollution (Box 14)
        - Federal legislation (Box 14)
        - Water Policy study (Box 14)
      - Waterways Commission
        - General (Box 14)
        - Keith Wilson file (Box 14)
        - Great Lakes diversion (Box 14)
        - Ontonagon (Box 14)